Mike Schaekermann

University of Waterloo mschaeke@uwaterloo.ca +1 (647) 573-2908

cs.uwaterloo.ca/~mschaeke

OVERVIEW

My research focuses on developing methods to capture and utilize the structure of ambiguous classification problems in the context of human-centered machine learning and human-AI collaboration. My work has a special focus on medical data analysis.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Candidate, Computer Science University of Waterloo, ON, Canada Advisors: Edith Law and Kate Larson

Bachelor of Science in Engineering, Media Informatics 2014

2016 - 2020 (expected)

Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria Thesis Supervisor: Lennart Nacke

State Examination (equivalent to BSc), Medicine
University of Marburg, Germany

2011

AWARDS & HONOURS

Google PhD Fellowship (\$45,000/year)	2018-2020
Best Paper, ACM CSCW	2018
Graduate Excellence Scholarship (\$5,000) — UWaterloo	2017
David R. Cheriton Graduate Scholarship (\$10,000) — UWaterloo	2016
International Doctoral Student Award (\$11,760/year) — UWaterloo	2016
Amazon Web Services Research Grant (\$7,000) — Amazon	2016
Merit-based Scholarship — Salzburg University of Applied Sciences	2014
Engineering Scholarship — Economic Chamber of Salzburg	2013
Nominee for the German National Academic Foundation	2009

SELECT PUBLI-CATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

- [C.1] Schaekermann, M., Beaton, G., Sanoubari, E., Lim, A., Larson, K., & Law, E. Ambiguity-aware AI Assistants for Medical Data Analysis. CHI'20. Honolulu, HI.
- [C.2] Schaekermann, M., Cai, C. J., Huang, A. E., & Sayres, R. Expert Discussions Improve Comprehension of Difficult Cases in Medical Image Assessment. CHI'20. Honolulu, HI.
- [C.3] Schaekermann, M., Beaton, G., Habib, M., Lim, A., Larson, K., & Law, E. Understanding Expert Disagreement in Medical Data Analysis through Structured Adjudication. CSCW'19. Austin, TX.
- [C.4] Cohen, R., Schaekermann, M., Liu, S., & Cormier, M. Trusted AI and the Contribution of Trust Modeling in Multiagent Systems. AAMAS'19. Montréal, Canada.
- [C.5] Schaekermann, M., Goh, J., Larson, K., & Law, E. Resolvable vs. Irresolvable Disagreement: A Study on Worker Deliberation in Crowd Work. CSCW'18. New York City, NY. Best Paper Award

- [C.6] Schaekermann, M., Ribeiro, G., Wallner, G., Kriglstein, S., Johnson, D., Drachen, A., & Nacke, L. E. Curiously Motivated: Profiling Curiosity with Self-Reports and Behaviour Metrics in the Game Destiny. CHI PLAY'17. Amsterdam, Netherlands.
- [C.7] Jaini, P., Chen, Z., Carbajal, P., Law, E., Middleton, L., Regan, K., Schaekermann, M., Trimponias, G., Tung, J., & Poupart, P. Online Bayesian Transfer Learning for Sequential Data Modeling. ICLR'17. Toulon, France.
- [C.8] Wehbe, R. R., Mekler, E. D., Schaekermann, M., Lank, E., & Nacke, L. E. Testing Incremental Difficulty Design in Platformer Games. CHI'17. Denver, CO.

Peer-Reviewed Journal Publications

- [J.1] Schaekermann, M., Hammel, N., Terry, M., Ali, T. K., Liu, Y., Basham, B., Campana, B., Chen, W., Ji, X., Krause, J., Corrado, G. S., Peng, L., Webster, D. R., Law, E., & Sayres, R. Remote Tool-Based Adjudication for Grading Diabetic Retinopathy. Translational Vision Science & Technology. 2019.
- [J.2] Williams, J., Cisse, F.A., Schaekermann, M., Sakadi, F., Tassiou, N.R., Hotan, G., Bah, A.K., Hamani, A.B.D., Lim, A., Leung, E.C.W., Fantaneanu, T.A., Milligan, T., Khatri, V., Hoch, D., Vyas, M., Lam, A., Cohen, J., Vogel, A., Law, E., & Mateen, F. Smartphone EEG and remote online interpretation for children with epilepsy in the Republic of Guinea: Quality, characteristics, and practice implications. Seizure. 2019.
- [J.3] Phene, S. and Dunn, C. and Hammel, N. and Liu, Y. and Krause, J. and Kitade, N. and Schaekermann, M. and Sayres, R. and Wu, D. and Bora, A. and Semturs, C. and Misra, A. and Huang, A. and Spitze, A. and Medeiros, F. and Maa, A. and Gandhi, M. and Corrado, G. and Peng, L., & Webster, D. Deep Learning and Glaucoma Specialists: The Relative Importance of Optic Disc Features to Predict Glaucoma Referral in Fundus Photographs. Ophthalmology. 2019.

Peer-Reviewed Workshop Papers and Abstracts

- [P.1] Schaekermann, M., Beaton, G., Habib, M., Lim, A., Larson, K., & Law, E. crowdEEG: A Platform for Structured Consensus Formation in Medical Time Series Analysis. 8th Workshop on Interactive Systems in Healthcare (WISH) at CHI'19. Glasgow, UK.
- [P.2] Schaekermann, M., Beaton, G., Habib, M., Lim, A., Larson, K., & Law, E. Capturing Expert Arguments from Medical Adjudication Discussions in a Machine-readable Format. 2nd Workshop on Subjectivity, Ambiguity and Disagreement (SAD) in Crowdsourcing at WebConf'19. San Francisco, CA.
- [P.3] Williams, J., Cisse, F.A., Schaekermann, M., Sakadi, F., Tassiou, N.R., Bah, A.K., Hamani, A.B.D., Lim, A., Leung, E.C.W., Fantaneau, T.A., Milligan, T., Khatri, V., Hoch, D., Vyas, M., Lam, A., Hotan, G., Cohen, J., Law, E., & Mateen, F. Utilizing a wearable smartphone-based EEG for pediatric epilepsy patients in the resource poor environment of Guinea: A prospective study. Annual Meeting of the American Academy of Neurology AAN'19. Philadelphia, PA.
- [P.4] Schaekermann, M., Lim, A., Larson, K., & Law, E. Expert Disagreement in Sequential Labeling: A Case Study on Adjudication in Medical Time

Series Analysis. 1st Workshop on Subjectivity, Ambiguity and Disagreement (SAD) in Crowdsourcing at **HCOMP'18**. Zurich, Switzerland.

[P.5] Schaekermann, M., Law, E., Williams, A. C., & Callaghan, W. Resolvable vs. Irresolvable Ambiguity: A New Hybrid Framework for Dealing with Uncertain Ground Truth. 1st Workshop on Human-Centered Machine Learning at CHI'16. San Jose, CA.

CONFERENCE WORKSHOPS ORGANIZED

Subjectivity, Ambiguity and Disagreement in Crowdsourcing. Co-chaired with Chris Welty, Lora Aroyo, Praveen Paritosh, Anca Dumitrache, Jennimaria Palomaki, Alex Quinn, Olivia Rheinhart, & Michael Tseng at WebConf'19.

Designing for Curiosity: an Interdisciplinary Workshop. Co-organized with Edith Law, Pierre-Yves Oudever, Ming Yin, & Alex Williams at CHI'17.

RESEARCH & WORK EXPERIENCE

Student Researcher, Google Health, Mountain View, CA 2018 - present

Research Intern, Google Brain, Mountain View, CA 2018

Visiting Researcher, Inria Bordeaux, France 2017

Software Engineering Intern, Google, Mountain View, CA 2017

Head of IT & Co-Founder, Stilnest.com, Berlin, Germany 2011 - 2015

Visiting Researcher, Ontario Tech University, ON, Canada 2013 - 2014

Research Assistant, University Medical Center, Marburg, Germany 2009 - 2010

TEACHING

Human-Computer Interaction (CS449), Teaching Assistant Winter 2018 University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (CS486), Teaching Assistant Fall 2017 University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Graduate Research Skills Seminar (CS697), Guest Lecturer Fall 2017 University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Introduction to Computer Science II (CS116), Teaching Assistant Spring 2017 University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (CS486), Teaching Assistant Fall 2016 University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Applied Mathematics, Tutorial Class Instructor2012-2013Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria2012-2013

FUNDING

Waterloo Citizen Science Laboratory

2016

Prepared a grant application with Edith Law and Alex Williams to provide infrastructure for scientific crowdsourcing studies. \$144,703 awarded through the Canadian Foundation for Innovation (CFI).

Prepared a grant application with Alex Williams to secure funding for computing resources to support various crowdsourcing studies and online hybrid human-AI systems. \$7,000 awarded in credits through Amazon Web Services (AWS).

SERVICE & LEADERSHIP

Journal Reviewer: ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems (2017) Conference Reviewer: CHI (2017-2020), CSCW (2018/19), CHI PLAY (2016)

Program Committee: CrowdBias 2018, HumBL 2019

Other: Session chair for "Designing Decision Support" at CHI 2019, Glasgow; President of the students council (2013) at Salzburg University of Applied Sciences

REFERENCES

Edith Law, PhD co-supervisor

Assistant Professor, Computer Science, University of Waterloo

Email: edith.law@uwaterloo.ca

Kate Larson, PhD co-supervisor

Professor, Computer Science, University of Waterloo

Email: kate.larson@uwaterloo.ca

Rory Sayres, Internship Mentor

Staff Researcher, Google Health Research & Innovations, Google

Email: sayres@google.com

Michael Terry, Fellowship Mentor

Staff Software Engineer, People+AI Research, Google

Previously Associate Professor, Computer Science, University of Waterloo

Email: michaelterry@google.com